<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A threefold preseruatiue against three dangerous diseases of these latter times 1. Non proficiency in grace. 2. Fals-hearted hypocrisie. 3. Back-sliding in religion. Prescribed in a sermon at S. Pauls Crosse in London, September, 17. 1609. By William Sclater, Batcheler in Diuinity, and sometimes fellow of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852072</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1583:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A threefold preseruatiue against three dangerous diseases of these latter times 1. Non proficiency in grace. 2. Fals-hearted hypocrisie. 3. Back-sliding in religion. Prescribed in a sermon at S. Pauls Crosse in London, September, 17. 1609. By William Sclater, Batcheler in Diuinity, and sometimes fellow of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By S. S[tafford] for Richard Bonian and Henry Walley, and are to be sold in Pauls Churchyard at the spred Eagle, neere the great north doore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The words "1. Non proficiency .. in religion." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A²  B-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at S. Pauls Crosse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Cropped.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Threefold Preſeruatiue <hi>againſt three dangerous diſeaſes of theſe</hi> latter times.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Non proficiency in grace.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Falſ-hearted hypocriſie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Back-ſliding in Religion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Preſcribed in a Sermon at S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe in London, September, 17. 1609.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Sclater, <hi>Batcheler in Diuinity, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fellow of the Kings Colledge in Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 3.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl> Take heed, brethren, leſt at any time there be in any of you an euill heart, and vnfaithfull, to depart away from the liuing God. But exhort one another daily, while it is called to day, leſt any of you be hardned through the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne.</q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>S. S.</hi> fox <hi>Richard Bonian</hi> and <hi>Henry Walley,</hi> and are to be ſold in Pauls Churchyard at the ſpred Eagle, neere the great North doore. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull, Maſter IOHN COLLES, <hi>Eſquier, at Wilch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe in Sommerſet, mercy and peace be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I haue often catched at ſome oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, to giue publike teſtimony of my thankefull remembring your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Fathers kind euery, performed to me. A duty it was, to preſent freely: to me a Kindneſſe, that I was ſelected. The recompence expected I haue carefully made good, by inſtructing my people; with what induſtry, God knowes: with what fruit (I thanke God) many ſoules can witneſſe. This kind of teſtimony I the rather embraced, for that it afforded occaſion, to cleare my ſelfe of ſome fond impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and of ſtopping the mouthes of vnreaſonable men, that (euen for paines) haue made me their by-word. It were long, to reckon vp all ſlanders of the malicious. Theſe are the chiefe, <hi>Vnlearned, ſingular, turbulent, factious.</hi> As touching <hi>Learning,</hi> I neuer much vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but <hi>by the grace of God I am that I am.</hi> He knowes much,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 3 10 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 2.2 <hi>Act.</hi> 7.22</note> that <hi>knowes Chriſt crucified and the vertue of his reſurrection:</hi> yet, had I the learning of <hi>Moſes, who was ſkilled in all the learning of the Egyptians,</hi> yea, the knowledge of men and Angels, I would endeuour in preaching to obſcure my ſelfe, that the power might bee knowne to be of God For <hi>Singularity,</hi> this is mine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology; ſingle I may go, (more ſhame for thoſe ſhould keepe me company:) ſingular, I am ſure I am not, ſith neyther I affect loneneſſe (would God all the Lords people were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, all Prophets, labourers!) and the courſe I held, is
<pb facs="tcp:17375:3"/> preſcribed with a thundering adiura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, hauing euer alſo bene holden by all faithfull Paſtours. The way of trauell is indeed leaſt trauelled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.15.</note> and <hi>Iſſachar loues his eaſe:</hi> yet thus I reſolue; rather then loſe heauen, to go alone; and neuer to be ſo good a fellow, as to run (with Idlers) to hell for company. My <hi>Turbulentnes,</hi> let theſe things witnes; my parting with many rights for peace ſake: diſgeſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, I ſay, not onely without Reuenge, but euen without ſeeking for iuſt defence: raylings, ſlanders, aſsaults, hazard of life, indeed what not? and vnleſſe they will indite mee for not admitting <hi>ſicam totam</hi> into my bowells,<note place="margin">Cic. pro Roſc. Amerin.</note> I know not what ſhow of turbulentneſſe they can accuſe me of. For <hi>Faction,</hi> let my courſes ſpeake: in regard of the Church, for doctrine <hi>I</hi> teach none but what ſhe profeſſeth: for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, throughout conformable to the orders preſcribed. If this be the matter, <hi>that the multitude is deuided,</hi> the cauſe would be inquired, whether mine, or Gods. Not where diſſentions are, there preſently is the Preacher facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. It hath euer bene one <hi>Accidentall</hi> effect of the Goſpel, <hi>to worke ſeperation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.51.</note> ſhall <hi>I</hi> ſay, betwixt a man and his neighbour? nay, betwixt a man and his child: nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a man and himſelfe. And let others pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their peaceable Miniſtery, <hi>I</hi> ſhall neuer thinke hee knowes the vſe of the <hi>Fanne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12</note> that is, alwaies toſsing, and makes no ſeperation. My comfort is in the middeſt of theſe trialls:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12</note> 
               <hi>Thus perſecuted they the Prophets that were before me.</hi> Concerning this preſent Sermon your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may thus vſe it with profit: as <hi>1.</hi> a ſpurre to Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. <hi>2.</hi> a whip for Security. <hi>3.</hi> a preſeruatiue againſt Apoſtaſy. The Lord graunt you and yours, me and mine, the whole Church of God a right vſe of it. And thus iudge of the Authour; Hee wiſheth you more good, then he can do you, and reſts euer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your thankfull &amp; obſeruant fauourite,</hi> William Sclater</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From your Pittmiſter:</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>October, 10. 160<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:3"/>
            <head>A THREE-FOLD <hi>preſeruatiue againſt three dangerous</hi> diſeaſes of theſe latter times.
<list>
                  <item>1 Non-proficiency in grace.</item>
                  <item>2 Falſ-hearted hypocriſie.</item>
                  <item>3 Back-ſliding in Religion.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 6.4, 5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> For it is impoſſible that they which haue bene once enlightned, and haue taſted of the heauenly gift, and haue bene made partakers of the holy Ghoſt:</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> And haue taſted of the good word of God, and of the powers of the world to come:</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> If they fall away, ſhould be renewed againe to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſeeing they crucify againe to themſelues the Sonne of God, and make a mocke of him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Scripture was of old peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Nouatians, to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their deſperate hereſie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying pardon and place for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to men falling through infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity after baptiſme:<note place="margin">Ambroſ. de Peniten lib. 2. cap. 2.</note> and at this day, through miſunderſtanding, hath proued the racke of many a weake conſcience: herein Nouatians againſt themſelues, that they thinke pardon cannot be obtained for any ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:17375:4"/> againſt knowledge and conſcience.<note place="margin">Bellar. de iuſt. lib. 1. Cap. 14. Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius vbiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Of late it hath bene wreſted to proue, that euen caſt-awaies may be by faith vnited vnto Chriſt, truely iuſtified: as truely ſanctifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d as Gods owne children, prepared to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory: with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence onely, <hi>permanency of penitency, or recouerableneſſe in the elect, inſtability in reprobates.</hi> And with as great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, though leſſe probability vrged to proue, that Gods children <hi>choſen to ſaluation, called according to his purpoſe,</hi> may (at leaſt for a time) fall from the ſtate of grace, loſe iuſtification not onely <hi>in foro conſcienciae,</hi> and in reſpect <hi>of feeling,</hi> but euen <hi>before God:</hi> loſe ſanctification, both in reſpect of <hi>exerciſe and meaſure,</hi> as alſo <hi>the very habit.</hi> The more diligence is required of vs in the vnfolding of it. For the context therefore, it lyeth thus. Cap. 5.12. &amp;c. is ſet downe a ſharpe reproofe of the people, for their <hi>non proficiency</hi> in knowledge and obedience: that hauing had ſo long time, &amp; plentiful meanes of bettering themſelues in grace, they ſtill ſtucke in the rudiments, and very ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſtian Religion. In this Chapter verſe 1. is an exhortation to greater progreſſe: <hi>Let vs be led forward to perfection.</hi> The Argument perſwading it, is layd downe in this text, taken from the danger of ſtanding at a ſtay: for hereby they hazard themſelues to vtter Apoſtacy and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from grace receiued. And how fearfull that ſtate is, it here ſhowne, euen deſperate and paſt recouery: wherfore to auoide it, they muſt haſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perfection. In forme thus, <hi>If by not proceeding we incurre dang r of reuolting, then muſt we be led forward to perfect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. But the firſt is true. Therefore</hi> &amp;c. The propoſition is omitted, and in ſtead thereof, the proofe is ſet downe, verſe 4.5.6. The aſſumption taken for granted: the concluſion expreſſed, verſe 1.</p>
            <p>Before particulars be preſſed, ſuffer a little to cleare the text from gloſſes of Nouatians, and others. What their hereſie was, is not hard to collect from Saint <hi>Cyprian, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiph. lib. 2. cap. 59.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> &amp; others. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> moſt briefly thus expreſſeth it: Men falling after baptiſme can neuer find
<pb facs="tcp:17375:4"/> mercy or pardon with God. The mitigations that ſome haue ſought out of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> &amp; others, I meane not to ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, all being in the iſſue equiualent. What they ſpeake of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying penance and pardon by the Church, was a meere ſhift and euaſion, whereto they were driuen by force of argument: beſides that, the Lord ordinarily binds and looſeth by Miniſteriall power of the Church. Now I hold it a good rule for iudgement of expoſitions, that is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily giuen by Diuines: <hi>where we find a ſence croſſing any truth, taught in plaine texts of Scripture, of it wee may ſay, it was neuer the ſence intended by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Being we now this gloſſe and inference to this touch.<note place="margin">Cyp. Epiſt. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cap. 2. &amp; Epiſt. ad Nouati. Aug. t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 4. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>q. mixt. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89.32.33.</note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thus re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſoned againſt Nouatians, from plaine texts of Scripture my purpoſe is not to recite their word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, leſt I waſte time. Their reaſons are theſe. Firſt, from the promiſe of God made to <hi>Dauid,</hi> (perhaps with referen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to <hi>Salomons</hi> fall) If any ſinne, <hi>I will viſit with the rod, but not remooue mercy.</hi> Secondly, from the nature of GOD in compariſon to earthly parents: was there euer father found ſo void of fatherhood, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the teares of a penitent prodigall hath not made to melt, and that hath not embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſubmiſſion of the moſt graceleſſe ſonne?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17 <hi>Pſa.</hi> 103.15. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.25.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſpare you, as a father ſpareth his owne ſon: as a father hath compaſſion on his children ſo the Lord on them that feare him.</hi> If any father be ſo obdurate, <hi>can a mother forget her child, and not haue compaſſion on the ſonne of her wombe? Though they ſhould forget, yet will not the LORD forget his.</hi> Thirdly, from examples of GODS dealing with his children repenting; <hi>Dauid, Peter, Iſraelits.</hi> 4. From the fact of God inuiting to repentance ſuch as were fallen. The Church of <hi>Epheſus fallen from her firſt loue;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apo.</hi> 2.4, 5, 20, 21.</note> of <hi>Thya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyra,</hi> that had <hi>committed fornication, and eaten meats ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to Idols,</hi> ſuffered <hi>Iezabel to teach and to deceiue:</hi> yet are inuited to repentance: ſhall we ſay, <hi>and not promiſed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don? Miſeranda fraternitatis irriſio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp. Epiſt. lib. 4. cap. 2.</note> Oh miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:17375:5"/> mockage of the brethren, thus to inuite to practiſe and deny the fruit of repentance; As if a man ſhould ſay to a huſbandman, Go to, vſe thy beſt ſkill and paines in tilling and manuring thy ground, ſow thy ſeede: but har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt looke for none. He blunts the edge of induſtry, through deſpaire of recompence.<note place="margin">Veniam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gando incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuum auferu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t penitentie. Ambr. de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. lib. 5. Cap. 1.</note> And by denying par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, theſe take away the greateſt inciteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to repentance.</p>
            <p>For this Scripture know wee, there is <hi>Lapſus</hi> (falling,) and <hi>Prolapſio</hi> (falling away:) the place not vnderſtood of particular ſlips, but of vniuerſall relapſing to a courſe of impiety.</p>
            <p>See we now the ſecond inference, and in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der examine the gloſſe. Reprobates (they ſay) may be iuſtified, ſanctified, what not, except ſaued? Behold a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Diuinity; that euer reprobate ſhould be iuſtified in Gods ſight,<note place="margin">Cata doran cata diatheſin cata meros.</note> or truely ſanctified by his Spirit! It is true, ſomething they may haue like it: ſo like, that themſelues and others may thinke them ſanctified. Secondly, a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition &amp; preparation that way they may attaine. Thirdly, ſome parts of it they may partake:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.9.19.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 11.27.28. Poculum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morcalitatis, quod confec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmitate noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, et virtute diuina, habet quidem in ſe vt omnibus proſit: ſed ſi non bibitur, non proficit. Aug. ad artic. ſalſo impoſ. Art. 1.</note> but to be iuſtified in Gods ſight, or truely ſanctified, and yet be reprobates, theſe are <hi>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ata</hi> (me thinks) in Diuinity: for, 1. iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; renouation depend vpon election: and they are termes conuertible, <hi>elect and ſanctified; ſanctified &amp; elect.</hi> Secondly, what mad man would once dreame, that they can euer be iuſtified by Chriſts bloud, for whom he neuer intentionally ſhed it? We haue a diſtinction of <hi>ſufficiency</hi> and <hi>efficacy:</hi> ancient I confeſſe and true. The ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is moſt true: <hi>The cup of immortality that had its confection of humane infirmity and diuine power, hath in it ſufficiency to benefit all; but if it be not drunken, it profits nothing.</hi> But what is this to the queſtion? The queſtion is touching the intention of Chriſt, in laying downe his life for a price of redemption, and of God the father, in ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son into the world, whether euer he had ſuch a meaning as to ſaue a reprobate: and (me thinks) it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiuable,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:5"/> that the Lord ſhould from eternall decree not to haue mercy, &amp; yet ſend Chriſt into the world with purpoſe to ſaue a caſt-away. Beſides, I hold it a true poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that for whom Chriſt merited remiſſion of ſinnes and the fauour of God, for him alſo he merited the donation of the Spirit, and the grace of perſeuerance, theſe being all equally parts of his purchaſe. Thirdly, who can imagine an influence of grace from Chriſt the head, where is not reall and true vnion with him? and who will vndertake to proue, that euer reprobate is vnited vnto Chriſt, fith hee lacks firſt, bond of vnion, <hi>the Spirit;</hi> ſecondly, inſtrument of vnion, <hi>liuely faith;</hi> thirdly, fruit of vnion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.21.22.</note> 
               <hi>euerlaſting life.</hi> It is true, that Chriſt is head ouer reprobates in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>eminence,</hi> not ſo in regard of <hi>influence.</hi> And the gifts they partake from Chriſt, they haue from him <hi>as a rich Lord adorning his Church;</hi> not <hi>as members of his body, by deriuation from the head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching this text, ſome gifts are here mentioned, <hi>illumination,</hi> &amp;c. but not ſuch as neceſſarily imply renoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Spirit. The maine is wanting, <hi>viz.</hi> renewing of the heart to vnfaigned loue of God in CHRIST, which I could neuer beleeue to be in a reprobate.</p>
            <p>As to the third inference, that Gods elect children cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according to his purpoſe, may loſe righteouſneſſe, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, &amp;c. that is more improbably deduced out of this text, then eyther of the former. I will not trouble you with thoſe vſuall diſtinctions of <hi>reality, and ſence habit &amp; exerciſe, ſubſtance and meaſure.</hi> Their meaning is, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch may wholly loſe Gods fauour, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification for the time. Now ſurely if this were ſo, yet this text of all others is moſt impertinently alleadged to that purpoſe, no place affoording plainer proofe of their vninterrupted abiding in the ſtate of grace. For thus I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: <hi>It is impoſſible for any man enlightned, &amp;c. and wholly fallen from grace, to be renewed by repentance:</hi> and ſhall wee ſay, it is impoſſible for an elect child of God to riſe by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?
<pb facs="tcp:17375:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Then ſure it were poſſible they ſhould neuer be ſaued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.23.</note> but not poſſible that Gods child ſhould be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo, as to faile of ſaluation. It remaines therefore that they neuer fall wholly from grace receiued. What needs more proofe?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8.</note> The ſpirit is in them <hi>ſemen manens &amp; immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals.</hi> Immortall? why ſo? Forſooth (according to theſe mens glozing) becauſe dying, he reuiues. A ſtrange gloſſe, nay rather, becauſe he neuer dyeth in them: for ſo we ſay, the ſoule is immortall, becauſe it dyeth not; the body mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, though it riſe againe. Shall I adde more reaſons? take theſe from the actions of God. Firſt, confirmation, and eſtabliſhment in grace <hi>eos telous,</hi> vnto the end, without interruption.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.3. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. De Nat. et dig. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. di. Cap. 6. 1. Ioh. 3.9.</note> Secondly, liberation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euills, by preuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: in euils, by ſuſtentation: out of euils, by giuing iſſue.</p>
            <p>Would you haue the iudgement of Ancients? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they write (moſt of them) doubtfully in this point: yet who ſo deſires their ſentence, let him read what <hi>Auſtine</hi> hath <hi>De bono perſeueranc.</hi> ſoundly for this purpoſe: and <hi>Bernard</hi> (if that booke were his) <hi>de Nat. et dign tate Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diui.</hi> alledging to this purpoſe the place of <hi>Iohn: Hee that is borne of God, ſinneth not, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe, ſayth he, ſuch a man <hi>patitur peceatum, non facit:</hi> &amp; preuenting that obiection from the fals of <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter:</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> thus, <hi>Charitatis in eo nequaquam facta eſt abolatio, ſed quaſi quedam ſeporatio.</hi> As Chriſt ſpeakes of the woman in the Goſpel, <hi>She is not dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theo. in Luc. 12.</note> 
               <hi>but ſleepeth.</hi> And <hi>Theophilact</hi> thus paraphraſeth the ſpeech of our Sauiour: <hi>Quamuis breuitempore concutiendus ſis, habet tamen recondita fidei ſemina: ſi ſolia abiecerit ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus inuadentis, radix tamen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, et non deficiet fides tua.</hi> He loſt his leaues, not his roote.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lyra. ad locum.</note>For this Scripture ſome thus anſwere: <hi>impoſſible,</hi> that is, <hi>difficult.</hi> That good father <hi>Latimer</hi> much pleaſed himſelfe in this euaſion. And it is true, that <hi>impoſſible</hi> with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> acceptation; but to my knowledge Scripture neuer ſo vſeth it.<note place="margin">Amb. de pen. lib. 2. Cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> a little otherwiſe; impoſſible to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to God: that is, impoſſible it ſeemes to vs to obtaine,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:6"/> yet poſsible through Gods gift:<note place="margin">Heb 10.26, 27, 28.</note> but neyther doth <hi>Ambr.</hi> himſelfe ſticke to this anſwere, &amp; the Apoſtle in another placed, ſerves the weaknes of it. Some thus: <hi>ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are no poſitions.</hi> And its true, that <hi>copulatiues</hi> ſomtimes haue force of <hi>conditionals.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> But ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> plainely affirmes a poſſibility of reuolti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I thinke we may yield, theſe words are no empty bugbeares to aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight vs with all, but ſuch as intimate a poſsibility of reuolting: for ſome men, no queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſome <hi>enlightned &amp;c.</hi> for none <hi>truly regenerate.</hi> And we ſhall a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on heare, that none of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> graces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true renouatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Spirit of God. Thus much in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rim for clearing of the text.</p>
            <p>Let vs now ſee the particulars of it. They are chiefly theſe three. Firſt, <hi>neceſſary of proficiency.</hi> Secondly, <hi>progreſſe of a Reprobate.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>peril of Apoſtacy.</hi> For the firſt,<note place="margin">The firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in the text.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs be led forward to perfection; For it is impoſſible, if we fall away, euer to be renewed to repentance Fulminat,</hi> me thinks, <hi>non loquitur</hi> His words are not words, but thunderbolts to rouze <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; taking it for granted, that there is no <hi>medium,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſeeming ſufficiency &amp; certayne Apoſtacy, videt ſcala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iacob,</hi> ſayth <hi>Bernard: et in ſcala Angelos, Iacob</hi> in a viſ on ſaw a ladder, &amp; on it Angels:<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnar. epiſt. 255.</note> where was none ſeene ſitting or ſtanding ſtill: but all eyther aſcending or deſcending: to giue vs to vnderſtand (Its <hi>Bernards</hi> gloſſe) that in the ſtate of this mortal life, there is no meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>profection</hi> and <hi>defection:</hi> but as we ſee our bodies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies on her growing or decreaſing, ſo muſt the Spirit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies either better it ſelf, or be impaired. But what though the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be defect o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? Beloued, me th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nks, we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the mention of them. <hi>Its impoſſible that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch men ſhould be renewed.</hi> Behold a moſt miſerable condition. It had bene better neuer to haue knowne, then knowing to turne backe. There is no ſinne done in ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore calling, but is capable of pardon: <hi>Paul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> blaſphemy,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Manaſſes</hi> his cruelty, <hi>Abrahams</hi> idolatry, <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> adultery. But for Apoſtacy, that is a ſinne irrecouerable, no place for pardon or repentance: God in his iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giuing ouer to hardnes of heart, &amp; impoſſibility of repentance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:7"/>
            <p>Let me adde one other reaſon. Its an vndoubted cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of all graces, where they are in ſoundnes, that they are growing.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47</note> 
               <hi>If you haue taſted how ſweete the Lord is,</hi> there will be a deſire to increaſe more and more. There iſſues from out the ſanctuary waters, euen the waters of life: ſee their encreaſe. Firſt, to the uncles, then to the knees, then to the loines, afterwards <hi>a riuer that no man could paſſe: The trees growing by this riuer, that bring foorth new fruits accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their moneths.</hi> What ſhould let to interprete, not onely of the progreſſe of the Goſpell, but of the efficacy of Gods Spirit in the hearts of his children? And for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>1.17.</hi> Clem. ſerom. log. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſearch and ſee whether there be any grace ſound that growes not. From <hi>faith</hi> to <hi>faith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Clemens:</hi> The Apoſtle ſeemes to ſpeake of a double faith, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of one, but increaſing continually, euen to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Infinite might I be this way: wherefore if eyther wee would preuent the danger of Apoſtacy, or prouide for our preſent comfort by aſſurance of ſoundnes, how need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is it to be led forward to perfection?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de verb. Apoſtol. Ser. 5.</note>Giue leaue then to exhort with <hi>S. Auguſt. ſemper adde &amp;c.</hi> Be alwaies adding, alwayes walking, alwayes profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And in any caſe take heed how we take a ſtand in this holy way of the Lord, or euer admit of one thought of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backwards. <hi>Lots</hi> wife, euen for caſting an eye backe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Sodem,</hi> became a piller of ſalt, an euerlaſting monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods wrath vpon Apoſtates. The vices then here noted, are: Firſt, <hi>ſtanding at a ſtay.</hi> See <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. And let me apply it to theſe ſlowback times. <hi>Vbi ſunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, qui deſcere ſolent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et.</hi> vbi ſupra</note> 
               <hi>ſufficit nobis? &amp;c. Where are they that ſay we haue enough, we will be no better then our fathers? O mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nache, non vis proficere? Non Vis ergo deficere? Nequaquam:</hi> What then? Where I am, I will hold my ſelfe. <hi>Nec peior fieripatior, wee melior cupi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</hi> Beloued, he could not haue ſpoken fitlier to the ſtate of theſe times: <hi>Nee peior fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri patior, nec melior cupio.</hi> Would God it were not the Embleme of our Church. But I leaue this <hi>Polypus,</hi> &amp; come
<pb facs="tcp:17375:7"/> to our people.</p>
            <p>Marueilous hath God bene in his mercy towards vs in this kingdome, granting vs meanes of knowledge, ſuch as our fathers deſired to inioy, but could not inioy them. And as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of this people, <hi>for the time we might haue bene teachers:</hi> and would God it were not ſo, euen in congregations where the word hath bene moſt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, that they had neede <hi>to be taught againe the very firſt principles and rudiments of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> I will tell you ſtrange things, yet true; in places where the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell hath long bene taught, are people notwithſtanding found ſo groſſely ignorant of Chriſt Ieſus, that they know not eyther what he is, or why ſent into the world, what he wrought to procure redemption, or how they may be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of him. Neyther need we wonder there ſhould be weakenes, where is ſo groſſe ignorance, after ſuch plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtruction.</p>
            <p>What then ſhould be the reaſons,<note place="margin">Impediments of proficiency</note> of this ſo little or no bettering in grace? One is, <hi>Opinion of ſufficiency, Semper tibi diſpliceas,</hi> ſayth <hi>Saint Auguſtine.</hi> No maruell, if there be ſo little care of proficiency, where there is ſo proude a conceit of perfection. <hi>I ſtriue forward to perfection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13</note> ſayth the Apoſtle; what was his ſpurre? Opinion that he was not perfect. A ſecond is, <hi>Comparing of our ſelues with inferiors or equals, where yet meanes of bettering are not equall.</hi> Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with their <hi>modicum</hi> (ſay ſome) were ſaued; why not we? I will tell you in few words, <hi>where men commit much,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>they expect the more; where leſſe committed, leſſe is expected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Proceed we, <hi>The way of the righteous ſhineth as the light, that ſhineth more and more to the perfect day.</hi> It was a wonder in <hi>Ioſua</hi> his time, that <hi>the Sunne ſtood ſtill:</hi> a greater,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 10.13. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20 11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.4.</note> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell in the dayes of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when <hi>he went backe ſo many degrees.</hi> Strange, that our Church ſhould ſtand at a ſtay; more wonder (me thinks) and horrour alſo, that ſhee ſhould go backward. <hi>You did run well,</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>who did let you? I haue a few things againſt thee, that thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:17375:8"/> loſt thy firſt loue.</hi> Me thinks, when I but mention theſe things, we ſhould iudge our ſelues the people here meant. For, what is become of that ancient deteſtation of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and his corruptions? while we begin to thinke, we may ſeparate too farre from Antichriſt, as Antichriſt; and to ſtudy (as ſome to-fore) compounding of the two Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions:<note place="margin">Caſſander</note> when as ſoone ſhall we compound light with darknes, Chriſt with Belial, as CHRIST with Antichriſt, Gods pure worſhip with Popiſh ſuperſtition. Shall I adde this one particular further? let it not be offenſiue. Time was, when we knew to put difference betwixt profeſſed enemies, and friends to vs in affection, though peaceably diſſenting from vs in ſome ſmall poynts of iudgement. And then ſeuerity ran her courſe againſt the greateſt and moſt Capitall enemies. How is it now, that Iuſtice knows no <hi>epiegcegan</hi> towards friends, &amp; is ſo full of conniuence towards obdurate enemies? Me thinkes yet, the ſword of Magiſtracy, ſhould be <hi>diſtomos,</hi> two-edged; &amp; if it pearce ſo deepe as the fleſh, and bones of friends, it ſhould bee ſheathed in the bowels of vnreconcileable aduerſaryes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.13. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. Mortmaine.</note>Let me come now to our people; That ſingular loue to Miniſters, <hi>for their works ſake,</hi> what is become of it? that <hi>double honor for them, that labour in the word and doctrine? Moſes</hi> of old was faine to proclaime a <hi>Sufficit,</hi> and ſtatutes were once made with vs to reſtraine ouerlauiſh contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thoſe were the times of <hi>giuing,</hi> theſe are of <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing.</hi> And (brethren) at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> firſt riſing of the Goſpell amongſt vs, <hi>how did the kingdome of heauen ſuffer violence? The word of God was precious in thoſe dayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.1.</note> As the Iſraelites when they firſt ſaw <hi>Manna,</hi> cryed out in wonder, <hi>Man-hu: what is this</hi> ſo excellent food, that the Lord hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed vs? ſo we of the Goſpell, admiring the rich grace of God, that began to ſhine vnto vs in the face of IESVS Chriſt. How are we now ſated with the plenty of it, and cry out contemptuouſly, Nothing but this <hi>Manna,</hi> The world peſtered with preaching<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To ſay nothing of that temper, which many of vs begin to hold euen in Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and to be halfe perſwaded, there may be, <hi>Virtutis
<pb facs="tcp:17375:8"/> nimium,</hi> too much precizenes euen in morall dutyes, and abſtinence from euill. But leaue we theſe vlcers, &amp; come to the ſecond thing in the text.<note place="margin">The ſecond member of the text. The firſt ſtep of a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</note> The progreſſe of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, for ſo I iudge it, becauſe their fall is without reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery. Their degrees are fiue, Firſt, <hi>Illumination,</hi> that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as naturally men know not the things of GOD, nor can know them; walke in the blindneſſe and vanity of their minds, embracing errour for truth, darkeneſſe for light, the Lord thus farre vouchſafeth grace euen to Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, that they ſee and acknowledge the truth of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, diſtaſte errours, diſcerne, acknowledge, approue that which is truth in Ieſus Chriſt. That Caſtawayes go thus farre, <hi>Peter</hi> playnely affirmes, ſpeaking of ſome men,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, 20.</note> 
               <hi>cleane eſcaped from thoſe, that are wrapped in errours, who yet are intangled againe and ouercome.</hi> What need many inſtances? Come not very Reprobates in the laſt day profeſſing, that they <hi>haue prophecied in Chriſts name?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22 <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.1</note> and was not <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> as his fellowes, inſtructed in the truth of the Goſpel, when diſmiſſed with the reſt to preach the Goſpell? I might be infinite this way.</p>
            <p>How then is knowledge by our Sauiour made a pledge of eternall life? <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3. Anſ. Knowledge of God in Chriſt, admits ſundry differences, according to <hi>Meaſures, Mannor, Efficacy.</hi> Firſt, there is a <hi>confuſed</hi> knowledge of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Chriſt; much like that light,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9 Mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ontes.</note> which men poare-blind haue of things farre diſtant. Such for the moſt part is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Reprobates. To heare how fluently thoſe men can diſcourſe of the ſecrets of Nature, how diſtinctly they vtter things, which naturall reaſon apprehends, it many times breedes admiration in the mindes of the hearers. But when they come to ſpeake of the myſteries of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, alas, how confuſedly tumble they out their little or no apprehenſion? that euery man may ſee they are but ſmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers in the ſecrets of Chriſt. The knowledge of Gods children is much more <hi>diſtinct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there is <hi>a generall</hi> knowledge of CHRIST <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and Redemption by him wrought; and there is <hi>another particular.</hi> In <hi>generals</hi> ſome caſtawaies go farre, perhaps beyond the Elect children of GOD. But to Iobs know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge neuer came Reprobate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I know that (my) Redeemer liueth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2 20 <hi>Pſ.</hi> 66.16. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10</note> to Pauls neuer, <hi>Chriſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (me) and gaue himſelfe for (me.)</hi> neuer to Dauids, <hi>I will tell you what he hath done for (my) ſoule.</hi> Thirdly, there is a Knowledge conſiſting <hi>in Theorie;</hi> there is another which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is ioyned with <hi>ſence and experience;</hi> when we know and feele the power of Chriſts death,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10</note> and the vertue of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. In <hi>the Theoricall</hi> excell the wicked, not ſo in <hi>the Experimentall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, there is an <hi>Idle and vnfruitfull Knowledge;</hi> there is againe a Knowledge that is <hi>mother of holy obedience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3</note> And this <hi>diſtinct, particular, experimentall, practicall</hi> Knowledge is that, that vndoubtedly accompanieth ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Let me apply it thus to theſe times, full of ſcience, voyd of conſcience; wherein how many bleſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this that they know, and yet know not, in what poynt of knowledge they out-ſtrip a Reprobate? Try the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light which is in thee, whether it be more, then may be in the children of darkneſſe. For which purpoſe, to the former diſtinctions adde alſo theſe two characters. Looke firſt, <hi>If Humility be ioyned with Knowledge. Knowledge</hi> (vn-ſanctified) <hi>puffeth vp</hi> the heart,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2</note> and makes it ſwell with contempt of our Brethren. Now would God there were not too euident footſteps of this vncharitable deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our brethren! How are our papers ſtuffed with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous ſpeaches of them? Engliſh diuines, Nouices, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becedaries in diuinitie, are now the beſt ſpeaches we can affoord our fellow-labourers, perhaps leſſe trauelled in the Ancients than our ſelues, yet as fruitfull in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, as they, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to them ſelues ſeeme greater Clearks. Alas (beloued) <hi>who hath ſeperated thee? or what haſt thou, which thou haſt not receiued?</hi> eyther what piety teacheth, to vpbtaid with Ignorance thoſe, who haue not reached to thy meaſure of ſcorning Knowledge? Ignorance (if any) would be pitied, not inſulted ouer, eſpecially in Brethren.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.21.</note> Conſider ſecondly, whether there be in thee <hi>a deſire of Communicating. The lips of the Righteous feed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17375:9"/> ſaith Salomon: and againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.7.</note> 
               <hi>The lips of the wiſe ſpread abroad Knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp; knowledge, where euer it is in ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is as new wine in veſſels deſirous of vent. What then may be thought of thoſe <hi>Seraphicall Doctours</hi> (as they would ſeeme the onely <hi>Gnaſticks</hi> of theſe times, for whoſe profound learning, no one ſoule can ſay he is the better?</p>
            <p>But I haſten to the next ſtep.<note place="margin">The ſecond degree.</note> 
               <hi>Haue taſted of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift.</hi> To omit the coniectures of others: This heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift I take to be <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> with thoſe treaſures of <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and righteouſneſſe,</hi> which the Lord hath ſtored vp in him, and tenders to euery of vs to be receiued by the hand of faith. <hi>If thou knoweſt the gift of God, and who it is, that ſaith vnto thee, &amp;c.</hi> Ioh. 4.10. Theſe latter words ſome take <hi>exegeticos,</hi> intimating that this gift, noted with that <hi>exoke,</hi> is <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe, <hi>made to vs of God, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare herewith Rom. 8.32. This then is the thing, which the Apoſtle affirmes, that euen Reprobates attaine vnto; <hi>viz. An ouerly apprehenſion of the excellency of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and the bleſſed eſtate of thoſe, that are made partakers of him by faith: they may ſee, what is the comfort of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes; of a conſcience ſprinkled with <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> bloud of Chriſt; of free acceſſe with confidence to the throne of grace. As <hi>Agrippa</hi> hauing heard Paul deliuer the ſumme of the Goſpell, the humiliation and glorie of Chriſt, the benefits thence accruing vnto vs, as one rauiſhed with the excellency of theſe things, cries out:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.28.</note> 
               <hi>Almoſt thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeſt me to be a Chriſtian.</hi> And Balaam, that wretch, beholding the bleſſed eſtate of Gods people, deſirous to partake with them in happines, paſſionately thus prayes: <hi>Oh that my ſoule might dye the death of the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>and my latter end be like his!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is then the difference, betwixt the ſweetneſſe, which Gods children find in Chriſt, and that which the Heires of perdition apprehend? Anſ. A child of God,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:10"/> ſeeing the excellency of Chriſt Ieſus, values him at ſo high a rate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scobala, Phil.</hi> 3.8.</note> as that for winning of him, he <hi>accounts all things dung and dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe,</hi> what euer profit it loſe him, what euer trouble it gaine him, he ſtriues as for life and death to be partaker <hi>of him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. 1. ad Iſehodor.</note> That pious cruelty, Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſpeakes of, you ſhall ſee in him; <hi>If father, mother, wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, any thing lye in his way to hinder him from Chriſt he treads all vnder foot for Chriſts ſake, and loues not life vnto death,</hi> hauing once taſted of the ſweetneſſe of his bloud, deſires to drinke deeper of it, yea though much bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Croſſe be therewithall mingled. With Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites it is farre otherwiſe: if wiſhing would winne him, they would not want him: or if together with him they might enioy the pleaſures of their ſinnes, nothing ſhould be more welcome. <hi>But to ſell all for Chriſt and his Croſſe, to exchange the treaſures of Aegypt for his rebuke,</hi> this is an hard ſaying: no Reprobate can endure it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third degree.</note>The 3. ſtep in their progreſſe followeth. <hi>Partakers of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Some hereby vnderſtand <hi>Renewing:</hi> I would beleeue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.14.</note> but that Chriſt tells me, <hi>He the Renewing ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides for euer, is immortall ſeed, a Well of liuing waters, ſpringing vp to life eternall.</hi> What then is the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> here mentioned? and how farre are they partakers of him? Anſ. What if we vnderſtand it of thoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gifts of the ſpirit, whereof in the hiſtory of the Acts is frequent mention? Learned Interpreters ſeeme not to diſſent. But let me adde ſomething more: Other gifts of the Spirit there are, which Reprobates partake; of kinne (perhaps) to ſanctification, but yet not ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17.</note> 1. That ſpirit of <hi>Compunction and Feare</hi> how many Caſt-awaies are poſſeſſed withall, howling euen with the voice of Dragons for their ſinnes, as cauſes of that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour wherewith their Conſciences are ſurpriſed? 2. Out of this <hi>Feare</hi> flowes an excellent meaſure, <hi>Externall refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and reſtraint;</hi> ſo powerfull, as (were it not the Iſſue diſcouers Hypocriſie) thou wouldſt ſweare they were <hi>true Nathaniels, right Iſraelites indeed.</hi> 3. Yea more
<pb facs="tcp:17375:10"/> then this, <hi>A wonderfull ſeruency of zeale</hi> for the Lord of Hoſtes. <hi>Come with me and ſee the zea e that I haue for the Lord,</hi> ſayth halting <hi>Iehu,</hi> 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. 16. 4. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude) with how many holy motions are ſuch men inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? how often heare they that voice behind them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ</hi> 30.21.</note> 
               <hi>This is the way, walke in it?</hi> yea purpoſes alſo conceiued, to follow the ſpirits guidance?</p>
            <p>In this point therefore, wherein do Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them? Anſ. That alwayes is accompliſhed in the <hi>Saints,</hi> which <hi>S. Paul</hi> prayeth for the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> that <hi>they are ſanctified throughout; in their whole ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>and ſoule and body,</hi> and that eſpecially in them is eminent, <hi>Their hearts are renewed to an vnfayned l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue of God in Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> ſo that whatſoeuer they do in Gods ſeruice, proceeds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fountaine, <hi>Loue of God in Chriſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.</p>
            <p>Followeth their fourth ſtaire.<note place="margin">The fourth degree. <hi>Luk</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>Haue taſted of the good word of God.</hi> I like that expoſition. <hi>The good word of God,</hi> that is, the Goſpell, <hi>that tidings of good things, and great ioy to Gods people.</hi> For herewith are the wicked affected euen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing. <hi>They receiue the word with ioy, Mat.</hi> 13.20.</p>
            <p>Now (briefly) the differences betwixt them and Gods children in reioycing are theſe. 1. <hi>Grounds of ioy</hi> in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Reprobates, are carnall; <hi>deepe myſteries, things nouellons and rare</hi> much affect them, <hi>as Athenians, Act.</hi> 17.20. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.37. 2. <hi>Miſunderſtanding:</hi> the <hi>promiſes</hi> rauiſh them, the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Conditions</hi> are diſtaſtefull; <hi>Reſtraints</hi> vncomfortable. As to malefactours in priſon, the tydings of a generall pardon after a Parliament, how welcome is it? the preface eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially runnes merrily; <hi>It pleaſeth the King of his mercifull inclination, to pardon all faults, and offences.</hi> But when the reſtraints come in the after-clauſe, <hi>Except murther, Treaſons, and Burglaries, &amp;c.</hi> how is all that ioy turned into mourning, and murmuring at the grace of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doner, from which they are excluded? 3. This ioy ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> like a flaſh of lightning:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20.</note> 
               <hi>Incontinently</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>they receiue the word with ioy.</hi> Whereas neuer was child of God <hi>ſuddenly</hi> brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hell to Heauen,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:11"/> from the diſcomfort of a wounded conſcience, <hi>preſently</hi> to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> reioyce in the Goſpell. 4. As <hi>ſuddenly</hi> wrought, ſo as <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and irrecouerably loſt;</hi> whereas the ioy of the Saints <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> is durable, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.22. 5. This ſweetnes once taſted by a child of God, by an heart ſeaſoned with grace, ſo affects them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.23.</note> that all things are ſooner parted with then the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. An Hypocrite likes well of the word, <hi>ad haras vſque,</hi> till it touch him in his earthly profits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> howbeit, rather then the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine ſhould periſh, Chriſt himſelfe ſhalbe <hi>entreated to depart out of their Coaſtes, Mat.</hi> 8.34.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The laſt degree. Caieton ad locum.</note>The higheſt pitch, they can reach vnto, remaines. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the powers of the world to come. Caieton</hi> (me thinkes) well aymes at the meaning. <hi>To taſte of the powers of the world to come,</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>is, when a man for the world to come, for the future reſurrection, and the laſt iudgement, begins to ſet vp the regiment of the ſoule ouer the body.</hi> Thus ſpeaks hee like a Philoſopher, of fleſh and ſpirit. Let me adde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for more diſtinct explanation. Men are ſayd <hi>to taſte of the powers of the world to come,</hi> when as the meditation of the life to come, beginning at the laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, works powerfully in their hearts. How powerfull this meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24.</note> we may ſee in <hi>many ſeeking to enter, but not being able.</hi> Take for inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thoſe poore ſoules in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Rome, <hi>drunken with the wine of that harlots fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> What volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary macerating of the body, diſtributing their goods, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning the world, ſee we in them, and all to purchaſe their heauen? Neuer were the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for their Idoll, then theſe for themſelues, to winne ſaluation. And ſhall we ſay they enter? If any man ſo thinke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31, 32.</note> I may commend his charity, but ſhall neuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue his iudgement. Heare the Apoſtle, <hi>Iſrael, which followed the law of righteouſneſſe, attayned not to the law of righteouſnes. Wherefore? Becauſe they ſought it not by faith, but as by the worke of the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The application is eaſie. And though I will not ſay, but that ſome man holding iuſtification by workes <hi>in
<pb facs="tcp:17375:11"/> theft,</hi> may perhaps be ſaued: yet this I think I may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old to affirme, whoſoeuer holds it <hi>in hypotheſi</hi> for his owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, a Iew, or Infidell may be ſaued as ſoone as he.</p>
            <p>What is then the odds betwixt Gods child, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate in this behalfe? Anſ. A Reprobate makes himſelf the onely or principall terme of his intention in all his performances; nor otherwiſe can deſire Gods glory, then as ſubordinate to his owne benefit. A meere <hi>mercenary</hi> affection ſhall you ſee in all ſuch: no one thing done of loue towards God, or with ſincere deſire to glorifie his name. Gods child, though he vſeth meditation of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a ſpurre to obedience, yet beholds ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond it, more to be deſired; that is, <hi>That God in all things may be glorified.</hi> And if euer the queſtion could come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Gods glory and the ſaluation of his ſoule, whether ſhould be preferred,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3.</note> rather had he be <hi>Anathema from Chriſt,</hi> then that the glory of GOD ſhould be impeached. Its an excellent ſpeach of <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. de diligendo Deo. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſine praemio d ligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Deut, etſi abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> praemit intuitu di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gendus ſit.</hi> and againe, <hi>Vacua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vera charitas eſſe non poteſt, nec tamen mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eſt.</hi> And this is the vndoubted character of our adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and regeneration to that <hi>immortall, vndefiled, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-fading inheritance, reſerued for vs in the heauens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now (brethren) for cloſing vp of this point,<note place="margin">Application. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> giue mee leaue to exhort, as the Apoſtle doth; <hi>Prooue your ſelues whether you be in the faith or no; examine your ſelues.</hi> Hee doubles the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe its a matter waighty, and of moſt difficult performance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Giue diligence to make your calling and election ſure.</hi> Beloued in Chriſt Ieſus, its no ſo ordinary a grace, as we commonly imagine, to be aſſured of ſaluation, or adoption. For behold, how many great things euen Reprobates attaine vnto! <hi>Knowledge of the myſtery of Chriſt; apprehenſion of his excellency; worthy gifts of the holy Ghoſt; reioycing in the Goſpell; many powerfull effects of the world to come;</hi> and yet are neyther choſen to ſaluation, nor indeed truely regenerate to a liuely hope
<pb facs="tcp:17375:12"/> in CHRIST IESVS. Alas (beloued) how many are there amongſt vs, boaſting of vndoubtfull aſsurance of ſaluation, that neuer reached to this ſcantling of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates!</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore againe, <hi>Proue we and examine ourſelues,</hi> ſift we theſe deceitfull hearts of ours to the bottome, that we may attaine ſome meaſure of wel grounded aſsurance, that we are the ſonnes of God. Let this alſo be the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone which the Lord ſeemes to commend vnto vs. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare we our meaſure of grace, with that wee find Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates to haue attained; nor let vs euer pleaſe our ſelues in any one, till we can ſay of euery one, <hi>Herein yet I goe beyond a Reprobate: Thus farre could neuer caſt-away aſcend.</hi> What if wee haue the knowledge of Chriſt? what if faith, ſo that wee could remoue mountaynes, and want obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Can that knowledge ſaue vs? can that faith aſsure vs? Behold, euen Reprobates alleadge for themſelues; <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22</note> 
               <hi>haue not wee prophecied in thy name? and in thy name caſt out Deuills?</hi> yet heare their vncomfortable diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Depart from me, I know you not.</hi> What though wee haue ſeene the excellency of <hi>CHRIST IESVS?</hi> can wiſh, as <hi>Balaam, our ſoules may dye as the righteous?</hi> what if we lament, with <hi>Eſau?</hi> take thought with <hi>Iudas,</hi> and wiſh our ſinnes had neuer bene committed? yea, what if our outward life be reformed and amended, and actions performed, ſauouring of vprightneſſe and zeale for the LORD? haue not Reprobates (I pray you) gone euen thus farre?</p>
            <p>Nor let any man ſay, that this is a deſperate and an vncomfortable doctrine; It is ſo, (perhaps) to preſumers, while ſuch: but tends in the iſſue to the greater and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger comfort and conſolation of GODS choſen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Hee hath comfort indeed, that hath ſuch as will hold out in the day of their temptation and triall. I neuer liked that <hi>Academicall Acatalepſy</hi> in this point of Gods loue and purpoſe to ſaue; for men to hang like
<pb facs="tcp:17375:12"/> 
               <hi>meteors</hi> in the aire, betwixt Heauen and Hell, doubtfull hope and ſlauiſh feare.<note place="margin">Bernard Ep. 190.</note> 
               <hi>Academicorum ſint aſtimationes iſtae</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard) quorum eſt dubitare de omnibus, ſcire ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil. Let vs leaue theſe thinkings to Academicks, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is to doubt of all things, and to be certaine of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They may make men hypocrites, can neuer worke ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and ſincere obedience. <hi>We loue God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he loued vs firſt.</hi> And it's impoſſible to loue him, till we haue his <hi>loue ſhed abroad in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> And let men ſay what they will, that it deſtroyes all care of good life, this yet is the truth; <hi>Thou neuer begin reſt to liue well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede,</hi> till thou know,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> that thou and thy workes are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with God, and ſhall certainely bee rewarded. Then runns a man chearefully in the race of Chriſtianity, when he knowes he <hi>runnes not at vncertainties.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26.</note> And it dulls the affection in well-doing, while we are ignorant, or doubtfull of our reward. But yet there is another rocke, as dangerous as this, at which many a ſoule makes ſhipwracke; that is, <hi>Preſumption.</hi> Yea I dare ſay, <hi>more periſh by preſuming, then euer did by deſpairing.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay againe with <hi>Peter, Bee diligent to make thy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and election ſure;</hi> and know, it is poſsible to attaine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, but thou hadſt neede bee diligent; <hi>God is not prodigall of ſuch graces, as do accompany ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing remaines; namely, <hi>The perill of Apoſtaſy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The third ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall branch of the Text.</note> 
               <hi>It's impoſſible for men thus enlightned, &amp;c. and falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, &amp;c. to be renewed to repentance.</hi> Let vs firſt waigh the termes, <hi>Falling, Impoſſibility, Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of fallings there are three degrees. 1. <hi>Lapſus; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſlips, or foiles,</hi> that euen Gods ſeruants take in wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt ſinne. Secondly, <hi>Declinations,</hi> or ebbings, (as I may terme them) of GODS grace in their hearts. Thirdly, <hi>Relapſing and falling away</hi> to a courſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:13"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</note>As touching particular ſlips, which <hi>Paul</hi> calles <hi>Parap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomata,</hi> we heard before what Nouatians taught, that euen theſe after Baptiſme were irrecouerable. Being preſt with diuers inſtances of Gods Saints, of whoſe repentance we read, as well as of their falles, and with thoſe Scriptures, which teſtifie our common infirmity, and Gods readines to ſhew mercy; at length they begin to reſtraine it to ſome particulars; as 1. <hi>Fornication.</hi> 2. <hi>Idolatry.</hi> 3. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eniall of Chriſt in perſecution.</hi> Theſe they taught, to be ſinnes of ſo high a Nature, as admitted no pardon, nor poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of repenting. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thus dealt by inſtance from poynt to poynt.<note place="margin">Lib. queſt. de vtroq. teſta. mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> 
               <hi>For fornication we haue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Dauids example.</hi> He might haue ſayd, for in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e t itſelfe <hi>Lot.</hi> And leſt any man ſay, This was in the old Teſtament true, not ſo in the new; beſides that (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerueth) it is incredible, that in this day of grace Gods mercy ſhould be ſcanted;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</note> what ſay we of that Inceſtuous perſon, for whoſe reſtoring againe into the Church, <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe becomes a Petitioner, and teſtifies, that <hi>his deliuery vp to Sathan was to this end, that his ſpirit might be ſaued in the day of the Lord Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>for Idolatry,</hi> the ſame Father thus reaſons from the Lords fact, inuiting a people deeply ingaged in this ſinne to Repentance, and proclaiming pardon: <hi>Quos vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad paenitentiam Dominus non horta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etur,</hi> (ſaith the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Martyr,<note place="margin">Cipri. ep. lib. 4. ep. 2. ad Anton.</note> and Biſhop, <hi>Saint Cyprian) niſi quia poenitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus indulgentiam pollicetur. The Lord would neuer exhort vnto Repentance, were it not that he</hi> (not onely purpoſed, but) <hi>promiſed alſo pardon to them repeating.</hi> He might haue added, as in other places, the promiſe of God to the Iewes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25.</p>
            <p>And <hi>for deniall of Chriſt through infirmity,</hi> how plaine an inſtance haue we in the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</note> denying, yea abiuring Chriſt Ieſus through feare of perſecution, yet brought to Repentance,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mb. de P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. lib. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.</note> and receiued to mercy? And as holy <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Numquid eadem eſt cauſa eius qui
<pb facs="tcp:17375:13"/> ſponte negat, et eius quem tormenta inclinauerint ad ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, non voluntas?</hi> Againe, <hi>Vicit eos poera non auertit perfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem ibid. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Item, Ipſius Diaboli de huiuſmodi lap is ſi requiramus ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, nonne videtur dicere, Populus hic labits me honorat, cor autem eorum longe eſt a me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal</hi> 6.1.</note> And what meanes the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, to bid <hi>Reſtore thoſe that are ouertaken by infi mity,</hi> if there be no hope of reſtitution? And the beloued Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>heſe things I write, that you ſinne not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Iob</hi> 2.1. Epi t. qua ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>but if any ſinne, we haue an Aduocate with the Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To leaue therefore this ſame <hi>Caninam herein,</hi> as Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an termes it, indeed <hi>the murtherer of the Brethren:</hi> Sinnes in this queſtion we muſt learne thus to meaſure, not ſo much b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>quantity of the matter,</hi> wherein they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as by the <hi>greatneſſe of that malice</hi> whereout they iſſue. The ſe ves blaſphemy was therfore vnpardonable, not becauſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laſphemy,</hi> but becauſe <hi>ex maleuolentia,</hi> ſaith Auguſtine iudicially.<note place="margin">Aug. vbi ſup.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond degree <hi>in falling,</hi> which is alſo recouerable, is that, which I tearmed Declination, or Partiall decay of the graces of God for a time, in reſpect of their ſenſible operation. Hereof read what the Spirit ſpeakes to the Church of Epheſu; <hi>Thou haſt left tby firſt loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.5, 6.</note> he meanes that feruour of affection, which before they had euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Yet <hi>repent and do thy firſt workes,</hi> there is hope of retaining thy Candleſticke.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw a winter of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> loue, yet liued to ſee their care ſpring and bloſſom afreſh. And who is there, euen of the moſt perfect, that feeles not theſe ebbings &amp; ſlowings of Gods grace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him? What then is that <hi>Falling</hi> ſo deſperate, here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned? Anſ. It is that <hi>totall Relapſing from grace receiued.</hi> I cannot in fewer or more pithy termes expreſſe it, then Maſter <hi>Iunius</hi> hath done before me, thus;<note place="margin">Paralel. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cap. 6.</note> when as a man falles, 1. <hi>Totus,</hi> 2. <hi>Ex toto,</hi> 3. <hi>In totum: The whole man in iudgement, will, affections, actions, from all grace, to all impious enormityes.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> thus, <hi>When a man turnes away from the holy Commandement giuen vnto him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>is againe
<pb facs="tcp:17375:14"/> intangled and ouercome, returnes like the Dog to his vomit, and with the Sowe to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> The Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſuch men, ſo falling, is impoſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> is of 2. ſorts: one <hi>Abſolute:</hi> the other <hi>ex hypotheſi.</hi> Abſolutely impoſſible it is not, they ſhould be renewed; for what contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> implies it? But ſuppoſing the vnchangeable wil of God to <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> contrary: ſo it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they ſhould euer repent; becauſe <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> righteous Lord hath determined thus to puniſh their malicious deſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repentance.)</hi> they may come perhaps <hi>ad metamelegan:</hi> ſo did Iudas;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 5.4.</note> and if the damned in hell befoole them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for impiety, why may not theſe men come to ſuch an after thought-taking, and wiſh, that their ſinnes had neuer beene committed? But to a godly ſorrow and change of their minds, <hi>ad metanogan</hi> it's impoſsible they ſhould euer be renewed.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> Therefore ſaith <hi>Peter; It had bene better neuer to haue knowne, then after Knowledge to turne backe: And their latter end</hi> (becauſe more hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, therefore) <hi>worſe,</hi> &amp; more diſcomfortable <hi>then their beginning,</hi> that is, then their ſtate before Calling.</p>
            <p>Will you now ſee the equity of this will in God? weigh 1. their fact in it ſelfe. 2. Compare it with <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> courſes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch as we all hold equall. For their fact, <hi>They crucify to themſelues againe the Sonne of God, &amp; expoſe him to infamy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture vſeth to implead our actions, not ſo much conſidering their euent, which the Lord by his power vſually diſappoints, as waighing our intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and the nature of our deeds, in themſelues conſidered. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>By thy meat ſhall thy weake brother periſh, for whom Chriſt died.</hi> Vnderſtand it not of the euent, but of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the action. So here, the Lord Chriſt (indeede) riſen from death, now dieth no more, but liueth for euer clothed with maieſty and honour. Yet, for that their facts in themſelues conſidered, are ſemblable to the curſed cruelty of the Iewes, they are ſayd againe to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify the Sonne of GOD. What? to make Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:17375:14"/> our pack-horſe for our wilful ſinnes? to fruſtrate (as much as in vs lieth) the end of his death? to draw him downe againe from Heauen, to make new ſatisfaction for our preſumptuous rebellions? to fill the mouthes of Pagans with blaſphemy of that holy name, after which we are named? What had the Iewes cruelty more execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in it? Such Miſ-creants, who will not ſay, but they are iuſtly depriued of the benefit of Chriſts ſacrifices and periſh eternally <hi>in fearefull expectation of vengeance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>and of violent fire to deuoure them?</hi> Againe, Compare the Lords dealing with that, which we all cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t equal amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt men.</p>
            <p>When a man hath ſpent the vtmoſt of his paine, and coſt, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill in manuring his ground, hoping to reape benefit by his induſtrious and coſtly huſbandry, yet finds no crop, but thornes and briefs; ſay we not of ſuch ſoyle, that it deſerues not the ſecond paynes of the owner, but to be left as a Deſart, and dwelling for wild Beaſtes? yea, to be accurſed for euer, and deuoted to the fire? And when the Lord hath laboured with ſuch barren hearts, ploughed vp their fallow ground, ſowne the ſeedes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, watered them with the dew of heauen, lookes (as iuſtly he may) for fruits of obedience, reapes none but the curſed fruites of contemning his graces and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Apoſtacy; is it not equall with the Lord, to giue hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart? to deſtinate to deſtruction, neuer to be recouered? This is the righteous Lords dealing with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates; this the recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he reapes, for all his paines beſtowed on them. Holy therefore, and iuſt, and equall is this will of God, in giuing vp ſuch to hardneſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsibility of repenting.</p>
            <p>Now (Brethren) we haue heard the meaning of the Text, we haue ſeene the truth of what is here taught,<note place="margin">Application.</note> with <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> equity of this iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God vpon their ſoules: Let me now exhort in the Apoſtles words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed</hi> (I ſay againe take heed) <hi>leſt there be in any of vs an euil heart, and vnfaithfull, to depart from the liuing God.</hi> Surely, except the Lord ſhould preſently ſend vs downe to the place of our iniquity, where is payne endleſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:15"/> eaſleſſe, &amp; remedileſſe, he could not inflict a greater iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then thus to permit vs to Apoſtaſie. And let no man ſay, this caueat concernes not him: <hi>If any man ſeeme to himſelfe to ſtand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>let him,</hi> (of all others) <hi>take heede, leſt he fall.</hi> Yea, I would to God, there were not too euident tokens, I ſay not of Apoſtaſie, but of declinings at leaſt to a worſe condition, in many of vs. There is beſide this <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall reuolting,</hi> another kind of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> which we call <hi>partiall,</hi> a fearefull incliner to this irrecouerable conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And it is of three ſorts. 1. in <hi>Iudgement,</hi> 2. in <hi>Affection,</hi> 3. in <hi>Practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>In Iudgement,</hi> when a man, in ſome particulars, falls fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoundnes and ſincerity of iudgement. The Apoſtle layeth this to the charge of the <hi>Galatians;</hi> that hauing bin rightly inſtructed in the meanes of iuſtification and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.3.</note> they were preſently <hi>carried away to another Goſpell; and hauing begun in the ſpirit, would be perfected in the fleſh.</hi> And are there not euidences ynow of ſuch <hi>Declinings</hi> in many of vs? We were wont to haue our Schooles and pulpits ring of this truth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Pope is Antichriſt, Rome Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, and that whoſoeuer wilbe ſaued, muſt forſake communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her.</hi> Of late we haue be thought our ſelues of a new See for Antichriſt: new Rome, rather then the old; a new Citty, ſet on ſeuen hills, neuer dreamt of till of late, diſcouered by Popiſh Geographers. But bleſſed be God that hath directed the heart and pen of our learned Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it. pref. prefix. Apol.</note> ſo graphically to be be paint him by his place, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, time of reuealing! &amp;c. So that now (I doubt not) Antichriſt ſhall againe be Antichriſt, Rome Babylon, and our people exhorted, not ſo much to bethinke themſelues of returning to Rome, as their mother, as to flye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſcarlet whore, <hi>made drunk with the bloud of Gods Saints.</hi> We were wont to be taught iuſtification by faith onely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out workes of <hi>Nature, Law,</hi> yea or of <hi>Grace</hi> it ſelfe. Shall we not ſay, they decline apace, that will haue workes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Iuſtification, <hi>tincta ſanguine Chriſti<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> died red in the bloud
<pb facs="tcp:17375:15"/> of Chriſt?</hi> Auricular Confeſſion we were iuſtly taught to deteſt, as a ſnare of mens Conſciences, a burthen not to be indured by Chriſtians. How then ſay ſome amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, there needes no more but a modification? ſeparate ſome few abuſes in the maner, the thing may well be reſtored in the Church. Theſe are ſtrange declinations: GOD graunt, not fore-runners of greater Apoſtaſy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In affection,</hi> when the heat of our zeale for God, &amp; loue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of his truth is abated in vs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.4</note> 
               <hi>I haue a few things againſt thee</hi> (ſaith the Lord to the Angell of Epheſus) <hi>that thou haſt left thy firſt loue.</hi> Shall I ſay, the Lord hath a few things, and not rather many againſt the Church of England, for leauing her firſt loue? where it that ancient ſeuerity and ſtrict hand ouer Papiſts? of whom I may well ſay, They are generally of the ſlauiſheſt nature of any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the Sunne; the very children of Hagar; a little of her Maſters indulgence what inſolency workes it? longer then ſhe feeles the rod of her miſtreſſe, ouer-inſolent. And who euer ſaw the fruite of lenity this way, that the number hath bin any way abated, and not rather increaſed by forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? How odious once was that Idoll of the Maſſe? when, if men would needs adore it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> it muſt be <hi>in the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their Imagery, made in the walles.</hi> Now (if Fame bee not too foule a lier) <hi>on euery hill, vnder euery greene tree,</hi> may the louers of the whore commit their fornications; yea, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in London, the eye of the Land, no where more frequent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Practiſe:</hi> when in manners we grow more diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and leaue our ſtrictnes. And here (beloued Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) where ſhould I begin to complaine? that which Iſaiah ſpeakes of Iſrael in reſpect of Gods Iudgements, is it not as true of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in regard of her ſinnes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>The whole head is ſicke, &amp; the whole heart heauy; from the crowne of the head to the ſole of <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  </hi> foote there is nothing ſound, but all full of ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and putrified ſores.</hi> The Court and City full of effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate delicacy; the Country of helliſh profaneneſſe; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:17375:16"/> ſhameleſſe in bribery; Miniſters euen benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with idleneſſe; the people generally become Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines in Religion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.7.</note> Beloued, <hi>yee did run well, who hath let you</hi> (ſtill) <hi>to obey the truth?</hi> Courtiers were wont to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their glory, &amp; he was of old eſteemed moſt honorable, that was moſt carefull to promote the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. How now begin they to caſt lots for Chriſts coate, and to ſhare amongſt them the portion of <hi>Leui?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.22.</note> things which amongſt the barbarous Egyptians were accounted holy? And when (till now) lacked the Engliſh Court ſome Tribunes of the people, carefull to keepe from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer-grieuous impoſitions? How do all men ſeeke their owne?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.21.</note> and <hi>almoſt pluck off the ſkinnes of the people? How is the faithfull City become an harlot? It was full of iudgement, and Iuſtice lodged there; but now they are become murtherers; their ſiluer is become droſſe, their wine mixed with</hi> worſe then <hi>water.</hi> It was wont to be reckoned the blemiſh of Germans, to be giuen to bowzing; Is it not ſo, that what was wont to be their ſhame, is now accounted our glory? <hi>to be mighty to drinke wine, &amp; ſtrong to powre in ſtrong drinke?</hi> To ſay nothing of that preſumptuous and euen defended prophanation of the LORDS Sabboths; that rifenes of Oathes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ie.</hi> 28.10.</note> euen in theſe dayes, when <hi>the land mournes for them.</hi> Are not theſe then apparent euidences of our decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings? And as I ſayd ere-while, God graunt they be not harbingers of greater miſchiefes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preſeruatiues againſt Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Speciall.</note>I will draw now toward concluſion, ſome few preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiues onely againſt this fearefull downfall ſhalbe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and then an end. Theſe, ſome of them concerne men of publique place, Magiſtrates and Miniſters; ſome, euery of vs, euen priuate Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">For Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates.</note>As touching Magiſtrates, they are or ſhould be, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the people, and meanes eſpecially to ſupport the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And firſt, by vigilancy. That charge of the Apoſtle giuen in generall to Gods people, belongs by an <hi>exoche</hi> to men in authority.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.15.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed that no man fall away from the
<pb facs="tcp:17375:16"/> grace of God.</hi> ſee another caueat Subordinate, <hi>Let no roote of bitternes</hi> (whether in doctrine or maners <hi>ſpring vp and trouble you, leſt thereby many be infected. Know you not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>that a little leauen leaueneth the whole lumpe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſayth he againe, pointing at corruption in doctrine, which ſame ſentence is alſo applyed to euill example in life; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, theſe are the things, requiring the ſpeciall vigilancy and care of Magiſtrates. We haue bin taught, not by <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> onely, but by the Lord himſelfe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>to reuerence the fulnes of the Scriptures.</hi> If any now ſhall ariſe, and deny the ſufficiency of them for determinations of all controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in ſubſtance or circumſtance of Religion, let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church officers hold and cenſure him, as a <hi>Deſtroyer.</hi> Wee were wont to exhort our people, old, young, men, women, to diligent conuerſing of the Bible: If any ſhall attempt to make encloſure of this common benefit to the Cleargy, let him taſt the ſeuerity of Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline. Theſe are Gangrenes (indeed) in the Church, &amp; ſuch ſpeaches as will <hi>encreaſe to more vngodlynes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The like I ſay of euill examples in life; if any ſuch ariſe, thither let the Magiſtrate haſten to reſtraine them. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in iudgement ſlow commonly from neglect of good life.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>They haue put away good conſcience</hi> (ſayth <hi>Paul</hi>) and then <hi>as concerning faith make ſhipwracke.</hi> This exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is often vſed to the Magiſtrates of this place; Wee heard the laſt day of 4. capitall ſinnes, raging amongſt you: my purpoſe is, to inſiſt in one onely, which (if any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) is the bane of all grace in the heart: that is, Adultery. <hi>whoredome and wine, &amp;c. ſteale away the heart.</hi> And it's true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ</hi> 4.11.</note> Adultety and Idolatry, they are contiguous vices: they were the very bane of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the wiſeſt King that euer raigned ouer Iſrael. And if my little obſeruance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me not, the great ſinne, as of this Land in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſo of this City eſpecial. I come not oft into your City; yet let me tell you what I ſaw in my very entrance vpon your ſuburbs: A woman, right of a Courtiſans behauiour, as <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribes her;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 7.</note> at whoſe gates (alas)
<pb facs="tcp:17375:17"/> how many young ſpend-thrifts waite, as weary of their patrimony and ſoules ſaluation? Right honourable, might it pleaſe you to be aduiſed, to obſerue the wayes of ſuch ſtrumpets: Theſe are they which, of all others, encreaſe tranſgreſſions amongſt men: theſe the Deuills very netts and ſnares, wherein (alas) how many are entangled euen to deſtruction? &amp; for this (no doubt) is the Lords dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full viſitation ſtill vpon vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.7, 9.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe men committed adultery, and aſſemble themſelues by companies in the barlots houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Country likewiſe ſwarmes with idle, ignorant, ſcandalous Miniſters. yea, I am perſwaded, all thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary Seminaries, that haue come vnto vs from Rome, neuer did halfe that harme in alienating our people from the truth, that theſe haue done by their enormous beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. It's thought, our petite diſſenſions are great cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of hardening in Popery: It may well ſo be. Howbeit this I dare affirme, they were neuer ſo great obſtacles to the courſe of the Goſpell, as the loytering, vnlettered, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute amongſt the Cleargy. Now Lord, that euer Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts ſhould haue cauſe to ſay of our Church; <hi>She held it a piaculum, not to weare a ſurplice, and a veniall ſinne, to be a lewd-liued Miniſter!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I adde (ſith I haue begun) one thing more, that may concerne Authority?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Par.</hi> 17.8, 9.</note> Of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſaphat it's ſayd, that when he went to plant Religion amongſt the people, and to preuent Idolatry, <hi>he ſent Leuites abroad into the cities of Iudah, to teach and inſtruct the people in the wayes of the Lord.</hi> Beloued, we haue a good-will (it ſeemes) to ſtop <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Popiſh ſuperſtition; many good proiects we heare of (to our great comfort) for that purpoſe: <hi>ſoſpitet Deus!</hi> I pray God proſper them! yet giue me leaue to aduiſe, that the principall be not neglected, I meane, furniſhing our Congregations with able and induſtrious teachers. I may boldly ſpeake it, It's neither ſeuerity of diſcipline, nor acuteneſſe of writing, nor ought elſe preuailes ſo much to roote out theſe ſtinking weedes of ſuperſtition,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:17"/> as the paines and diligence of learned &amp; well-liuing prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers. Let me therefore with reuerence aduiſe my Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, that care may be had to furniſh our people with able Paſtors, that may feede them with knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and if the preſent ſtore of Conformers ſerue not, might I not (in compaſſion of the Churches neceſſity) wiſh ſome conn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at thoſe, that diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for matters of circumſtance, whilſt yet they carry themſelues peaceably in the Church? The Lord would not haue Canaanites at once caſt out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.29.</note> 
               <hi>leſt the wild beaſts ſhould increaſe vpon his people.</hi> Suffer me then to plead for Iſraelites, that it may ſuffice them to lacke liuing, and the Church not be depriued of their paines: at leaſt let them helpe to be are our burdens, and draw water for the people out of the wells of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>I come to the Miniſtery: and firſt,<note place="margin">For Miniſters.</note> for our Brethren diſſenting from vs in iudgement of Ceremonies impoſed; let me intreat as in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt, ſeeing Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy is ſo much feared by them, that they would be well aduiſed, how they forſake their Mother in this her ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neceſsity: and not ſo wholly pleaſe themſelues in their iudgement, to refuſe peaceable Conference for their better information. I counſell no man to do ought (no not in things indifferent) with a doubting conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; fearefull are the examples of ſuch, as vn-reſolued yeeld to practiſe. Notwithſtanding, this let me propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be deliberated, <hi>whether ſhould not this be a Miniſters reſolution, To lay downe his Miniſtery for nothing, for which he ought not alſo to lay downe his life?</hi> And whether with comfort may a man leaue life, rather then we are a ſurplice in the Church of England? teaching (as no doubt, ſhe doth) and practiſing Gods pure worſhip, deteſting Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, vrging Ceremonies not for ornament, much leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Gods ſeruice, but for order and policy onely, and as a meane to teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie ſubiection to the lawfull power of the Magiſtrates?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17375:18"/>
            <p>For vs, who by Gods bleſſing retaine our ſtandings with comfort &amp; fruit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> howſoeuer it pleaſe ſome <hi>(whoſe ſeruants we are not)</hi> to cenſure vs of inſincerity for this very poynt of Conformity,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> let vs be exhorted <hi>to preach the word, to be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon.</hi> for the times ſurely are come prophecied of the Apoſtle, wherein that <hi>itch of the eare</hi> is riſe amongſt our people. And we heare alſo often vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings with the praeualence of Popiſh leauen, how many thouſands haue they peruerted, ſince his Maieſties happy entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into this Kingdome; and for my part I do part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue it:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.25.</note> For what maruell, if the <hi>Enemy ſow his tares, whiles the ſeruants ſleepe?</hi> I know not, how it is with you in this part of the Kingdome; in other places I am ſure, ſcarcely one of ſixe Congregations hath ordinary preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or almoſt rude Catechizing of the people. yea, ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is paines-taking growne amongſt Miniſters alſo, that very painfulnes is cenſured of preciſenes, and ordinary preaching enough, to bring vpon any man the crime of Puritaniſme, though neuer ſo conformable to the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline eſtabliſhed. Now, Brethren, conſider if this be to be preciſe, <hi>to labour in the word and doctrine,</hi> ought not all Gods miniſters to be thus preciſe <hi>in Action, not in Faction?</hi> ſayd one once elegantly. Be therfore exhorted (and but high time) to greater diligence, and let the vaunts of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts be vnto vs as the voyce of Nehemiah to the Iewes; <hi>You ſee our miſery:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.17</note> 
               <hi>Come and let vs build the walls of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, that we be no more a reproch.</hi> And for matter, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note> let it be that ſame <hi>adolon gala, the deceitfull milke of the word,</hi> without mixture with contrary or inferiour mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for this onely yeelds found nouriſhment vnto the ſoule. Is Fame a liar? or is it true, that thoſe and the like places of eminency in this Kingdome, ſound with little elſe, but Frierly conceits and alluſions? We were wont to plead ſtrongly for <hi>Fathers,</hi> that they might haue their audience in the Pulpitt, and for my part, I neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uied them their due reſpect. But if wee become <hi>a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:18"/> ad Fratres, from Orthodox Fathers to doltiſh Friers,</hi> and feede our people with the froth of their wits, what ſhal we ſay? God grant their conceits of wit proue not a ſnare, to draw downe the more poyſonous and bane-full drugges of their Popiſh hereſy.</p>
            <p>And here I had thought with reuerence to haue exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the reuerend Fathers of the Church, that as they are in higheſt places of dignity, ſo they would be the forwardeſt in this great worke of the Miniſtery. The rather would I haue preſumed to haue bin their Monitor, for that I haue obſerued, the Religion eſpecially of our Vulgar people, to hang (all-moſt all) on their ſleeues: we petit Miniſters (alas!) are the ſcorne of our people, in our moſt weighty and ſerious exhortations. Their words are held as Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, their lips alone thought to preſerue Knowledge. Sundry reaſons I meant to haue preſſed it withall; firſt, from the Excellency of this worke, aboue all other acts of the Miniſtery. For, for my part I muſt profeſſe, I cannot yet ſee, what that great and important buſineſſe of the Miniſtery ſhould bee, to which it may beſeeme Preaching to giue place. I am ſure not Sacraments. <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize</hi> (ſaith the holy Apoſtle) <hi>but to preach the Goſpell.</hi> He might as well haue ſayd,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.</note> not to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, not to do any thing, in this ſence, comparatiuely, as he deſires to be vnderſtood. Secondly, Is there any thing, more honourable? Heare the ſame Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim</hi> 5.17. Chryſ. ad locum.</note> 
               <hi>The Elders, that rule well, are worthy of double honour.</hi> Call it <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence</hi> or <hi>Maintenance,</hi> or both; how euer, a ſpecialty in it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to them, <hi>that labour in the word &amp; doctrine.</hi> &amp; ſure it is, more ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d honour is there to be gained in the hearts of our people by preaching, then by all outward helps whatſoeuer. Thirdly, what ſayd I? honour amongſt men? yea, more comfort to our Conſciences, and glory in Gods Kingdome. Heare Salomon; <hi>He that winneth ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.30. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>is wiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and Daniel, <hi>They that turne others to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, they ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres in the firmament,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17375:19"/> and <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>What is our hope, our ioy, our crowne of reioycing? are not you it in the preſence of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming?</hi> What comfort like this, when a Miniſter comes before the Lord the great Shepheard of the Sheepe, with the words of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 8.18.</note> applyed to our Sauiour? <hi>Lo mee, and the children, that thou haſt giuen mee!</hi> the ſonnes &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which by thy bleſſing I haue begotten vnto thee in the Goſpell! Fourthly, I would haue added hereto the example of their worthy predeceſſours. Beloued, I am ſo farre from thinking that there were <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church, hauing the care of Church diſcipline, that I begin to be of opinion, they were all <hi>Preaching-Elders,</hi> that had to do in ordination, and iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. The Apoſtles (we know) from whom our Reuerend Biſhops haue more then probably deriued their ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were all laborious this way. One of them, <hi>on whoſe ſhoulders lay the care of all the Churches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> yet cryes, <hi>Wo to him ſelfe, if he preach not the Goſpell.</hi> And <hi>Timothy,</hi> I preſume, was a Biſhop; yet hath that charge layd on him with an heauy adiuration,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>To preach the word.</hi> And for ſucceeding ages; thoſe Reuerend Biſhops, <hi>S. Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Chriſoſtome, &amp;c.</hi> what monuments haue they left vs more venerable then their pithy Sermons, and exhortations to the people? Let vs all therefore, euen Superiours, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, ſo much as infirmities of age, and the waighty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Church-gouernment will permit, to <hi>ſtirre vp the gift of God that is in vs,</hi> that if it be poſſible, <hi>we may ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the weake knees; and keepe that which is halting from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turned out of the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Generall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiues for all.</note>I come now to priuate Chriſtians, that they alſo may haue wherewith to preſerue themſelues from this feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diſcomfortable eſtate of Apoſtaſy. Their moſt ſoueraigne antidotes, are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Obedience according to their meaſure of knowledge receiued.</hi> This is the Chriſtian built on the Rocke,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>7.</hi> ad fin.</note> 
               <hi>that heareth the word of God, and doth it.</hi> On ſuch a man let the winds
<pb facs="tcp:17375:19"/> blow, the flouds beate, the raine fall, he ſtands neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vnmouable; for he is built vpon the Rocke. Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries boaſt much of their thouſand Proſelytes: I am perſwaded, if they were enquired of, they ſhould be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſuch, as neuer made any Conſcience of their wayes. Now ſure, we are beholden to them, that they haue receiued (like a Draught) the Excreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of our Church. Let them reioyce, and applaud themſelues in their Thouſands; for this yet take my warrant; They ſhall neuer winne credit to any Religion, whatſoeuer it is they profeſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Syncerity and vprightneſſe of the heart before God.</hi> Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I neuer knew right <hi>Nathaniel, true Iſraelite</hi> indeed, that proued a Reuolt; Nor euer could read of Hypocrite, but became Apoſtate, if euer trouble aroſe for the Goſpell. It's a true poſition, <hi>He that begins Religion in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy, ends in Apoſtaſy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Par.</hi> 25.2. <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.</note> Amaziah did many things <hi>ſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of vprightneſſe in the eyes of the Lord, but not with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit heart.</hi> What was his Iſſue? <hi>Returning from the ſlaughter of the Edomites, he brought the gods of Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, and ſet them vp to be his gods, and worſhipped them, and burnt incenſe vnto them.</hi> There is an <hi>Art</hi> in theſe times, that hath more Students, then any other of liberall or Manuall ſciences; <hi>the Art of ſeeming,</hi> eſpecially <hi>in Religion.</hi> City and Country, almoſt nothing but <hi>vizars.</hi> Now would God we could remember what Chryſoſtome ſayth; <hi>Hypocrite is it good, to ſeeme good?</hi>
               <note place="margin">in Matth. oper. imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</note> 
               <hi>it's farre better to be good. Is it euill, to ſeeme euill? it's farre worſe, to be euill, &amp;c.</hi> and the ſaying of Chriſt (me thinks) ſhould not be forgotten, <hi>To him that hath ſhall be giuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>and whoſoeuer hath not, from him ſhall be taken euen that which it ſeemeth that he hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Labour for aſſurance and certaine perſwaſion of the Truth in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> your owne minds;</hi> eſpecially, for <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> which is armour of proofe againſt Apoſtaſy, <hi>Experimentall ſenſe of Gods holy truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10</note> Thou ſhalt neuer feare infection in the poynt of Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if thou know the practiſe and experience of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. As on the other ſide, when men reſt onely vpon
<pb facs="tcp:17375:20"/> the authority of their Teachers and gouernours, hauing no better reaſons of beliefe and worſhip: no maruell, if they turne with the wind, and run current with the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and ſtreame of the times. And this is the lamentable vnſettlednes of our people, that they looke no farther for proofe, no not of faith and worſhip, then the Authority of the Magiſtrate. Now bleſſed be God, that hath giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Maieſty a right iudgement in matters of Religion; and the Lord that hath begun that good worke in him, perfect it vnto the day of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. But if (which be it farre from vs to ſurmiſe) if, I ſay, the Lord ſhould ſuffer him to fall,<note place="margin">To cagro dou leuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. me to Kurio, Rom <hi>12.11.</hi>
               </note> or in his wrath depriue vs of his gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if he ſhould permit vs to a Popiſh Ruler, who ſeeth not, how indifferent our people are? ſuch tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing is euen now rife; and that reading beſt pleaſeth; <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the time, not the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke not the aſſemblies and gatherings together of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 27.20.</note> 
               <hi>as the maner</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle, and we may ſay too) <hi>of too many it. Quench not the Spirit;</hi> wouldſt thou not quench him? <hi>Deſpiſe not prophecying.</hi> that's the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oyle for the lampe of the Sanctuary: not being ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therwith, thou ſhalt ſoone perceiue it to grow dimme, and by little and little to an vtter extinction. Now (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) to omit both Popiſh and profane Recuſants; Is it not to be lamented, that amongſt thoſe, who ſeeme moſt to bewaile the declinings of our Church, there ſhould be ſome found, ſo eyther nice or humorous, that they refuſe to arme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt that, which they ſo much feare and pity in others, by diligent attendance to the worke of the Miniſtery? One (forſooth) is too learned; another too plaine; a third too elegant; or elſe too rude; ſome too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall; ſome too ſcrupulous: none pleaſeth, but ſome one, whom our parciall conceits haue made our Idoll. So wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton are we growne with abundance! God graunt, the day come not vpon vs, when we would wiſh to run from ſea to ſea, to heare, and ſhall find no meanes. When chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:17375:20"/> begin to play with their bread, diſcreet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> take it from them, or keepe them ſhorter; &amp; let vs feare, leſt this delicacy bring on vs a ſcarcity of hearing the word of God. Home-deuotions are comfortable, if vſed in their ſeaſons; but we know who hath ſayd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.9</note> 
               <hi>The prayer of him, that turneth his eare from hearing the law, is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</hi> And if we would auoyde Apoſtaſy, take heede how wee forſake the gathering together of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beware, how the gariſhneſſe of the world dazle thine eye,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and bewitch thine heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Demas</hi> ouertaken with the loue thereof, forſakes <hi>Paul.</hi> And, <hi>Loue not the world</hi> (ſayth the beloued Apoſtle) <hi>the faſhion thereof paſſeth away;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>coſ nos para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getas:</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.17.</note> or as ſome render, the <hi>glittering ſhew thereof withdrawes and ſteales away the heart from God.</hi> How many haue our owne eyes ſeene, mirrours of holy carriage in their meane eſtate, whom the loue of aduancement, and the enioying thereof hath made ouer diſſolute? would God, not alſo ſcandalous to their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Keepe good conſcience preciſely,</hi> neyther allow thy ſelfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> in any thing, no not the ſmalleſt, which conſcience (rightly informed) condemnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is hee which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes not himſelfe in that which he allowes.</hi> As bleſſed he, that allowes not himſelfe in that which his heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes. Herein therefore be preciſe, <hi>Do nothing, no not the leaſt, with a doubting or recoyling conſcience.</hi> The ſtroke of Conſcience neglected in ſmall things, it growes by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible degrees to ſwallow greater, without reluctation. Fearefull are the inſtances we haue daily in this kind; But I ſpare to trouble you. One reaſon onely I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexe, to ſet edge on this exhortation, and then ſhalbe the end. Beloued in Chriſt Ieſus, The Lord hath long bene amongſt vs, by the heauieſt of his temporall iudgements. Thoſe arrowes of his diſpleaſure, <hi>Famine and Peſtilence,</hi> haue bene made almoſt drunken with the blood of our ſlaine. And yet (behold!) <hi>the wrath of the Lord is not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill.</hi> Wonder we at this,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:21"/> that the Lord ſhould walke thus ſtubburnly towards vs? More wonder it is (but that his mercies are endles) that wee haue not bin vtterly conſumed. For that which I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah ſpeakes of Iudah,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.5.</note> is it not true of vs, <hi>That wee fall away more and more?</hi> I can well remember, ſince the one halfe of theſe miſeries hath brought vs on our Knees in ſack-cloth and aſhes, in prayer and faſting for our ſinnes, that haue drawne downe the wrath of God vpon vs. And a man would thinke, theſe Afflictions ſhould haue that effect in vs, which the Lord teacheth to bee the end of his Iudgements,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15</note> 
               <hi>To make vs ſeeke him the more diligently.</hi> Oh, that it were not true, that wee harden our hearts the more, continuing and encreaſing our Apoſtaſies, ſcarce euer bethinking our ſelues of humiliation! As if we meant, to ſtout it out with the Lord, and to dare him to do his worſt. Oh,<note place="margin">Iob.</note> remember who hath ſayd, <hi>Hath any bin fierce againſt the Lord that hath proſpered?</hi> and what himſelfe threatens, viz.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>to walke as ſtubburnly towards vs, as wee can do againſt him;</hi> and to encreaſe our plagues ſeuen times more, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the lighter preuaile to humble vs. Some courſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore betimes let vs take, to ſtop <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> fierce wrath of the Lord, that is gone out againſt vs. <hi>It's a fearefull thing</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>to fall into the hands of the liuing God, who is in his wrath a Conſuming fire.</hi> If our houſes had taken fire, we haue this wiſdome to thinke, one bucket of water may do more good to ſtop the flame, then almoſt a riuer, when it hath begun to gather ſtrength. Would God, we were as wiſe for our liues and ſoules, as we are for the traſh of this world! Surely, more preualent to quench the fire of Gods diſpleaſure (in the beginning) is one teare, then a whole ſhowre &amp; ſtreame of them, when it's once inflamed. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this I know none, to ſtop <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> courſe of Gods wrath.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Par.</hi> 7.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>If I ſend peſtilence among my people, If my people, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom my name is called vpon, do humble themſelues, &amp; pray, &amp; ſeek my preſence &amp; turne from their wicked wayes, then will I heare in heauen, and be mercifull vnto their ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:17375:21"/> and will heale their land.</hi> Right honorable, why are not you a petitioner to thoſe in authority, that a Faſt may be proclaimed? Stay you, til you come againe to your thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in a weeke? Alas, how agrees that with Chriſtian compaſſion to thoſe, that in the <hi>Interim</hi> loſe wiues, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, thoſe that are deereſt vnto them? and what a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile and <hi>Pharoah like</hi> reſolution is this, neuer till needes muſt, <hi>to ſend for Moſes and Aaron,</hi> to intercede for vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Maieſty of God? I beſeech you therefore in the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus, if there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if any compaſſion and mercy; fulfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l my requeſt: im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune the performance of this duty; proue the Lord with theſe things, ſee if he rebuke not the Deſtroyer for your ſakes. <hi>If you conſent and obey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ</hi> 1 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>you ſhall eate the good things of the land. But if yee refuſe and be rebellious,</hi> God graunt I proue not a true Prophet, <hi>you and your children, and your people ſhalbe deuoured of the Peſtilence.</hi> If theſe things preuayle not with authority, let me yet admoniſh euery of vs, that in our houſes, by our ſelues and our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, we may be carefull this way: we ſhall then ſee that gracious promiſe performed to vs and ours, <hi>when thouſands fall at our right hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.7.</note> 
               <hi>and ten thouſands at the left, it ſhall not come nigh vs. Ezek.</hi> 9.4. A marke is ſet (by commaundement from the Lord) on the forheads of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe that mourne for the abominations that are done in the middes of Ieruſalem. And let vs be aſſured of the ſame LORDS protection for vs and ours, if we be ſuch, as from our hearts mourne for the deteſtable things are done amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of all grace, that hath called vs to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory by Ieſus Chriſt, make vs perfect, confirme, ſtrengthen, and ſtabliſh vs, that we may be kept blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vnto the day of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To him be glory and dominion for euer. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
